With twisted-pair Ethernet cable, there are
two wiring standards: 568a and 568b.
In 568a, pins 1 and 2 are white/green and
green, pins 3 and 6 are white/orange and orange,
pins 4 and 5 are blue and white/blue, and
pins 7 and 8 are white/brown and brown.
In a 568b standard, pins 1 and 2 are white/orange
and orange and pins 3 and 6 are white/green
and green.
A straight-through cable, which represents
most Ethernet cables, is used to connect unlike
devices to each other, like a PC to a switch
or a router.
When two like devices are connected to each
other, a crossover cable is used.
The reason for that is that when two like
devices are connected, they both want to send
and receive on the same wires, which will
cause many collisions of data.
Thus, the four wires primarily used for transmission
are crossed over so the data can transmit
freely from one device to another.